Guide to the Montana Mining Company Records 1882-1934
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Montana Mining Company Records
1882-1934
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 142
Montana Mining Company
34.0 linear feet
The collection focuses on the workings of two mining companies that owned and operated the Drumlummon mine in Marysville, Montana, over five decades.
Historical Note
Mining began in Montana in the 1850s, when traders for the Hudson's Bay Company discovered gold near present-day Deer Lodge. Little came of these early diggings but the territory continued to attract hopefuls and the first big strike took place near Bannack in 1862. In the next two years, gold was discovered at Virginia City and Last Chance Gulch in the heart of present day Helena. A dozen years after the first discoveries in Helena, Thomas Cruse filed for the claim on the Drumlummon. His discovery gave birth to the town of Marysville and one of the first rich mines in Montana. While the wealth produced by the Drumlummon pales in comparison with the later copper giants in Butte, the discovery of rich gold and silver deposits provided a tremendous boost to the Montana Territory's economy and spurred national and international investment.
The claim for this vein of gold and silver ore was filed by Thomas Cruse in 1876. He drove a tunnel into the vein over the next several years but reportedly went only 500 feet. In 1880, Cruse convinced William and Charles Mayger to construct a five stamp mill for processing ore from the mine. The ore was processed for a time and then a disagreement over royalty payments led Cruse to buy out the Mayger's interest in the mill. Word of the rich ore being mined at the Drumlummon reached beyond the borders of the Montana Territory. The Joint Stock Association, a London based company, organized to buy the Drumlummon Mine from Thomas Cruse in 1882. The following year they purchased the mine and created the Montana Mining Company, Limited. The company paid Thomas Cruse $1.63 million for the property and allowed him to retain a one-sixth ownership in the mine. Cruse used the profits to establish a bank in Helena and went on to be a successful and wealthy businessman.
The Montana Mining Company installed George Attwood as manager of the mine. He did a poor job and resigned after his first year when profits did not meet expectations. He was replaced by R.T. Bayliss, a capable manager, in 1884. The arrival of competent management coincided with a sharp rise in profits. Bayliss was replaced for a year by Henry Bratnober before returning to manage the mine through 1891. During this period almost 500,000 tons of ore were removed yielding $9.2 million. A feud between the Montana Mining Company and the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company erupted in 1889. The dispute centered on ownership of a vein being mined by both companies. The St. Louis Company filed suit to halt the Montana Mining Company's miners and the resulting apex litigation lasted until 1911. The suit ultimately reached the Supreme Court of the United States and cost nearly $400,000 in legal fees. The costs of the suit, the court decision in favor of the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company, and declining ore values at the Drumlummon forced the Montana Mining Company to sell the property at sheriff's sale in 1911. The stockholders of the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company received an impoverished mine in disrepair for all their litigation efforts. Management of the property shifted to William Mayger, the St. Louis Company's superintendent. After fierce corporate infighting, he was replaced in 1913 by Harry Quinby. The new manager lasted only briefly before he was ousted by William Mayger. For the next 20 years stockholder squabbles and failing finances kept the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company on the brink of collapse. During the final years there were constant shutdowns and stockholder assessments. The mines and mills finally closed in 1933, ending one of the richest mineral strikes in Montana history.
The collection is primarily a corporate history. The documents are focused on the workings of two mining companies that owned and operated the Drumlummon mine in Marysville, Montana, over five decades. The collection contains correspondence, papers for the Drumlummon Provident and Accident Insurance Association, financial records, governance, legal documents, and printed materials. The collection provides insight into the challenges of operating a mine in Montana. The majority of the collection consists of incoming correspondence. The letters generally are business oriented and are from suppliers of mining supplies and services that the Montana Mining Company and the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company used. The financial records include detailed accounting of the costs and rewards of the mine. The governance primarily concerns stockholder struggles to control the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company in the years after it took control of the Drumlummon property. The bulk of legal documents relate to litigation between the Montana Mining Company and the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company from 1890 to 1911. The remainder of the collection relates to all aspects of the routine functioning of an underground silver and gold mine in Montana.
The collection is divided into six series:
Series I: Correspondence, 8.5 linear feet, 1881-1934
Series II: Drumlummon Provident and Accident Insurance Association, 0.5 linear feet, 1888-1900
Series III: Financial Records, 4.0 linear feet and oversize materials, 1883-1933
Series IV: Governance, 1.0 linear foot and microfilm, 1886-1933
Series V: Legal Documents, 1.0 linear foot and oversize materials, 1875-1931
Series VI: Printed Materials, 0.5 linear feet, 1870-1989
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Gift of Dale Johnson, 1966.
The Montana Historical Society holds 5 linear feet of correspondence from the Montana Mining Company.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Montana Mining Company--Trials, litigation, etc.; St. Louis Mining and Milling Company--Trials, litigation, etc.
Drumlummon Provident and Accident Insurance Association; St. Louis Mining and Milling Company
Drumlummon Mine (Mont.)
Corporate governance--Montana; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Marysville (Lewis and Clark County); Gold mines and mining--Montana--Marysville (Lewis and Clark County); Silver mines and mining--Montana--Marysville (Lewis and Clark County); Mining corporations--Montana
Business records--Montana; Correspondence; Financial records; Legal documents
Montana; Labor History; Mines and Mineral Resources
- Correspondence, 1881-1934; Series I; 8.5 linear feet
  The series is arranged chronologically beginning in 1881. There is a single folder of outgoing correspondence for 1887 to 1890. The remainder of the series is all incoming correspondence dating through 1934. The bulk of the letters are from suppliers of mining goods and services. The letters range from national suppliers of sophisticated mining equipment like Fraser and Chalmers to local suppliers of hay for company stables. Many of the letters merely solicit business from the mining companies, attempting to sell everything from flint pebbles for ore processing to the services of a zither player. The letters from suppliers include information on the whole range of materials required by the two companies and the national scope of the mining business. Many of the letters concern the costs of supplies and the difficulty of shipping material to Marysville. The letters also relate to unpaid bills, mine injuries, job inquiries, and the personal matters of various managers. There are letters regarding other mining properties, price quotations, clippings from the Engineering and Mining Journal, and mining prospects at the Drumlummon. There are several items of particular interest in this series. The communications between the London headquarters of the Montana Mining Company and Marysville are generally in telegraphic code for secrecy. There are numerous code sheets to help company officials decode the messages. Slater's Telegraphic Code Book in Series VII also relates to this material. The correspondence relating to both companies also overlaps chronologically. Letters relating to the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company appear in the files nearly 20 years before they own the Drumlummon. There is also a report from a Pinkerton detective investigating union activity in Marysville and Butte. The series provides insight into the international nature of mining in Montana. The letters also detail the logistical and financial difficulties of running a mine.
  - Correspondence - Outgoing, September 1887 - January 1890 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - General Correspondence Marysville, 1881 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - General Correspondence Marysville, 1882 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - General Correspondence Marysville, March - June 1883 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - General Correspondence, July - September 1883 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1883 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1884 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - General Correspondence, April - July 1884 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - General Correspondence, August - December 1884 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - General Correspondence, January - February 1885 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - General Correspondence, March - April 1885 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - General Correspondence, May - September 1885 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1885 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - General Correspondence, January - February 1886 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - General Correspondence, March 1886 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - General Correspondence, April - August 1886 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1886 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1887 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - General Correspondence, May - June 1887 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - General Correspondence, July - December 1887 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1888 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - General Correspondence, April - June 1888 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - General Correspondence, July - September 1888 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1888 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1889 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - General Correspondence, May - August 1889 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - General Correspondence, September - December 1889 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1890 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - General Correspondence, June - September 1890 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1890 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1891 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - General Correspondence, June - September 1891 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1891 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1892 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - General Correspondence, April - June 1892 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - General Correspondence, July - August 1892 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - General Correspondence, September - December 1892 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1893 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - General Correspondence, April - June 1893 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - General Correspondence, July - December 1893 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - General Correspondence, February - September 1894 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1894 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1895 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - General Correspondence, June - December 1895 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - General Correspondence, January - June 1896 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - General Correspondence, July 1896 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - General Correspondence, August 1896 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - General Correspondence, September - December 1896 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1897 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - General Correspondence, April - November 1897 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - General Correspondence, January 1898 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - General Correspondence, February 1898 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - General Correspondence, March - April 1898 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - General Correspondence, June - December 1898 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - General Correspondence, January - July 1899 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - General Correspondence, August - October 1899 (Box-folder 7/8)
  - General Correspondence, November - December 1899 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1900 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - General Correspondence, June - September 1900 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1900 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1901 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - General Correspondence, April - May 1901 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - General Correspondence, June 1901 (Box-folder 8/7)
  - General Correspondence, July 1901 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - General Correspondence, August 1901 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - General Correspondence, September - October 1901 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - General Correspondence, November 1901 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - General Correspondence, December 1901 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - General Correspondence, January - February 1902 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - General Correspondence, March - April 1902 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - General Correspondence, May - June 1902 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - General Correspondence, July - October 1902 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - General Correspondence, November - December 1902 (Box-folder 10/5)
  - General Correspondence, January - February 1903 (Box-folder 10/6)
  - General Correspondence, March - May 1903 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - General Correspondence, June - September 1903 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1903 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1904 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - General Correspondence, September - December 1904 (Box-folder 11/5)
  - General Correspondence, January - February 1905 (Box-folder 11/7)
  - General Correspondence, March - May 1905 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - General Correspondence, June - July 1905 (Box-folder 11/9)
  - General Correspondence, August - October 1905 (Box-folder 12/1)
  - General Correspondence, November - December 1905 (Box-folder 12/2)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1906 (Box-folder 12/3)
  - General Correspondence, April - June 1906 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - General Correspondence, July - September 1906 (Box-folder 12/5)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1906 (Box-folder 12/6)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1907 (Box-folder 12/7)
  - General Correspondence, April - June 1907 (Box-folder 12/8)
  - General Correspondence, July - September 1907 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1907 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1908 (Box-folder 13/3)
  - General Correspondence, April - September 1908 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - General Correspondence, April - October 1909 (Box-folder 13/5)
  - General Correspondence, April - November 1910 (Box-folder 13/6)
  - General Correspondence, March - May 1911 (Box-folder 13/7)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1912 (Box-folder 13/8)
  - General Correspondence, August - October 1912 (Box-folder 14/1)
  - General Correspondence, November - December 1912 (Box-folder 14/2)
  - General Correspondence, January - April 1913 (Box-folder 14/3)
  - General Correspondence, May - August 1913 (Box-folder 14/4)
  - General Correspondence, September 1913 (Box-folder 14/5)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1913 (Box-folder 14/6)
  - General Correspondence, January - November 1914 (Box-folder 14/7)
  - General Correspondence, March - July 1915 (Box-folder 14/8)
  - General Correspondence, January - December 1916 (Box-folder 14/9)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1917 (Box-folder 14/10)
  - General Correspondence, April - June 1917 (Box-folder 14/11)
  - General Correspondence, July - September 1917 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - General Correspondence, October - December 1917 (Box-folder 15/2)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1918 (Box-folder 15/3)
  - General Correspondence, July - December 1918 (Box-folder 15/4)
  - General Correspondence, January - May 1919 (Box-folder 15/5)
  - General Correspondence, July - December 1919 (Box-folder 15/6)
  - General Correspondence, January - December 1920 (Box-folder 15/7)
  - General Correspondence, January - December 1921 (Box-folder 15/8)
  - General Correspondence, January - November 1922 (Box-folder 15/9)
  - General Correspondence, February - May 1923 (Box-folder 16/1)
  - General Correspondence, March - December 1924 (Box-folder 16/2)
  - General Correspondence, January - February 1925 (Box-folder 16/3)
  - General Correspondence, March - April 1925 (Box-folder 16/4)
  - General Correspondence, May - June 1925 (Box-folder 16/5)
  - General Correspondence, July - August 1925 (Box-folder 16/6)
  - General Correspondence, September - October 1925 (Box-folder 16/7)
  - General Correspondence, November - December 1925 (Box-folder 16/8)
  - General Correspondence, January - December 1926 (Box-folder 16/9)
  - General Correspondence, January - November 1927 (Box-folder 17/1)
  - General Correspondence, January - March 1928 (Box-folder 17/2)
  - General Correspondence, April 1928 (Box-folder 17/3)
  - General Correspondence, May - June 1928 (Box-folder 17/4)
  - General Correspondence, July - December 1928 (Box-folder 17/5)
  - General Correspondence, February - August 1929 (Box-folder 17/6)
  - General Correspondence, July - December 1930 (Box-folder 17/7)
  - General Correspondence, January - December 1931 (Box-folder 17/8)
  - General Correspondence, December 1932 (Box-folder 17/9)
  - General Correspondence, February 1933 (Box-folder 17/10)
  - General Correspondence, March - July 1934 (Box-folder 17/11)
  - General Correspondence, Undated (Box-folder 17/12)
- Drumlummon Provident and Accident Insurance Association, 1888-1900; Series II; 0.5 linear feet
  This brief series contains material relating to the Montana Mining Company's insurance subsidiary. The Association was limited to employees of the Montana Mining Company. The Board of Trustees was composed of two members elected by employees and two members appointed by the Company. The series includes a copy of the by-laws, rules, and regulations of the Association from 1900. The remainder of the series consists of the canceled checks of the Insurance Association dating from 1888 to 1897. These provide insight into the costs of running the Insurance Association and include both claims paid to workers and materials for administration.
  - Drumlummon Provident and Accident Insurance Association, 1888-1900 (Box-folder 18/1)
- Financial Records, 1883-1933; Series III; 4.0 linear feet and oversize materials
  This series is broken into several categories and arranged chronologically within each category. The categories within the series are arranged alphabetically. The series contains materials housed in traditional folders and a significant number of oversize materials. These are housed in oversize boxes and map cases. The bulk of this series is comprised of assay reports, bullion returns, and mill reports. However, there are folders for assets and liabilities, federal reports, insurance, invoices, mine progress reports, claim descriptions and names, payroll records, reports on other mines, and tax assessments. The materials in the series provide a solid background for understanding the finances of the Drumlummon mine and the two companies that owned it. The assay reports present a fairly complete picture of the ore values for the early years of the mine. The quantity of reports declines sharply after 1902 and is sporadic for the ensuing years. The bullion returns document the metal bars produced after smelting. These returns are less complete than the assay returns. They are intermittent for the entire history of the mine, although the period around 1900 is reasonably complete. Mill reports concern the quantity of the ore processed at each of the stamp mills that the companies operated. They also contain information concerning the quantity of pulp and tailings each produced and the values of the ore being processed. These reports are very complete through the early 1890's and include a set of blueprints for a 1913 mill. There are reports on several other mines in British Columbia, the Lucky Girl in Tuscarora, Nevada, and the Silver Bell in Montana. The Lucky Girl was owned by the Montana Mining Company and the reports include most financial aspects of the operations over eight years. The payroll records and invoices for the Drumlummon are incomplete but provide insight into the costs of running a mine. They also include crucial information about workers and the division of labor in the mines. The information on expenses and assets is very useful for understanding the difficulties of financing mining. The information is particularly detailed for the era between 1883 and 1907. There are detailed descriptions of the costs of individual shafts, mills, and payroll. The order books contain detailed records for all the goods required for the years from 1887 to 1897 and the orders for the Rose Densmore mine for 1890. The delivery book contains information for goods delivered from 1889 to 1897. There are folders containing information on tax assessments of the mines from 1888 to 1933 and the Federal Census of Mines for 1926 to 1933. There are a few insurance documents relating to death benefits for a miner and a fire insurance policy from 1913. There are also reports of equipment for the Marysville Electric Light and Water Company.
  - Assay Reports, 1883-1887 (Box-folder 19/1)
  - Assay Reports, 1883-1887 (Box-folder 32OS/1)
  - Assay Reports, 1888-1891 (Box-folder 19/2)
  - Assay Reports, 1888-1891 (Box-folder 32OS/2)
  - Assay Reports, 1892-1893 (Box-folder 19/3)
  - Assay Reports, 1894 (Box-folder 19/4)
  - Assay Reports, 1895 (Box-folder 19/5)
  - Assay Reports, 1896 (Box-folder 19/6)
  - Assay Reports, 1897 (Box-folder 19/7)
  - Assay Reports, 1898 (Box-folder 19/8)
  - Assay Reports, 1900 (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Assay Reports, 1901 (Box-folder 20/2)
  - Assay Reports, 1902-1904 (Box-folder 20/3)
  - Assay Reports, 1905-1906, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 20/4)
  - Assay Reports, 1913, 1915, 1917 (Box-folder 20/5)
  - Assay Reports, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 20/6)
  - Assay Reports, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 32OS/3)
  - Assay Reports, 1920-1929, undated (Box-folder 20/7)
  - Bullion Returns, 1885-1898, undated (Box-folder 20/8)
  - Bullion Returns, 1885-1898, undated (Box-folder 32OS/4)
  - Bullion Returns, 1900-1917 (Box-folder 20/9)
  - Bullion Returns, 1900-1917 (Box-folder 32OS/5)
  - Federal Reports: Census of Mines, 1926-1933 (Box-folder 21/1)
  - Insurance, 1893, 1913 (Box-folder 21/2)
  - Invoices, 1883-1922, undated (Box-folder 21/3)
  - Invoices, 1883-1922, undated (Box-folder 32OS/6)
  - Lucky Girl Mine Reports, 1900 (Box-folder 21/4)
  - Lucky Girl Mine Reports, 1901 (Box-folder 21/5)
  - Lucky Girl Mine Reports, 1906-1908 (Box-folder 21/6)
  - Mill Blueprints, 1913 (Box-folder 32OS/7)
  - Mill Reports, 1884-1885 (Box-folder 21/7)
  - Mill Reports, 1886 (Box-folder 21/8)
  - Mill Reports, 1885-1917 (Box-folder 35OS/1)
  - Mill Reports, 1887 (Box-folder 21/9)
  - Mill Reports, 1888 (Box-folder 22/1)
  - Mill Reports, 1889 (Box-folder 22/2)
  - Mill Reports, 1890 (Box-folder 22/3)
  - Mill Reports, 1891-1895 (Box-folder 22/4)
  - Mill Reports, 1896-1900 (Box-folder 22/5)